♪ [music] ♪
[doorbell buzzing]
- I'm Cory Booker.
Did you ever hear my name?
Cory Booker.
I'm not sure if you've heard of me,
but I'm the City Councilman
from the Central Ward,
but now I'm running for mayor.
Fellas, how you all doing?
- *[narrator] Cory Booker is a 32-year-old,*
*first-term city councilman,*
*running for mayor of Newark,*
*New Jersey's largest city.*
- [Cory] I'm coming after you.
- *[narrator] He's hoping to unseat
the long-time incumbent,*
*Sharpe James.*
- So, I can't believe you used to live in a house
where you keep the door open.
And now,
you're in a building where you're not even--
- [woman] I know. I know.
- It's outrageous.
- [woman]… You want a million locks
on your door.
- Yeah. Well, that's our #1 issue.
And no disrespect to Sharpe James,
but he's had 16 years to show you
what he could do.
And anything he could have done,
he should have done by now.
It's time for some new young blood,
okay?
Thank you! God bless you!
- [woman] Amen! Thank you.
- [Cory] Alright. Bye-bye!
- *[narrator] I've been documenting
the campaign for a few weeks now.*
*and I'm beginning to get a sense
of how many forces there are in this city*
*working against his candidacy.*
- *[Joe Foushee] Excuse me a sec.*
*My man, excuse me for a second.*
-$$ [Joe] You can't do it. Can't do it.$$
*-[Cory] What you saying man?*
-$$ [Joe] I can't let you do it.
I'm not gonna let you walk the hallways.$$
-$$[Cory] Joe, this is ridiculous.
Nothing we're here is illegal.$$
-$$[Joe] It's my name, I'll call the cops.$$
-$$[Cory] I think you need to call the police.
Let's continue guys.$$
*- [male voice] ... Councilor Booker.*
-[Cory] Hey, how are you, Sir?
I'm Cory Booker,
from the city of Newark Central Ward Council.
-[Pablo Fonseca] There's nothing illegal
with what we're doing.
Sharpe's people came this year--
just a couple of days ago.
-$$This is not a public building.
This is a private, you know, it's private.$$
- $$[Pablo] The Housing Authority's?$$
- [Cory] Yeah, you take care of yourself.
Buh-bye now.
-Other side, Councilman.
-Buh-bye now.
*-[Pablo] We'll just have to finish
and then we're going down.*
- *[Cory] They brought the big brass.*
[Cory laughing]
-[Cory] How you doing?
How you doing?
How you doing, Sir?
- *[policeman] Let's go, guys.*
- [Cory] Is this the kind of security
they get every night here?
[Cory laughing]
- [Pablo] Hey Cory.
- [Cory] Hey! How are you?
-[female voice] I'm fine.
- *[Pablo] Bringing out the Deputy Chief.*
- *[Cory] That's unbelievable.*
- *[Pablo] That's twelve cops,
for God's sake.*
- It's so ironic, man.
Here's a neighborhood
that never gets police protection.
But I show up and they get
the top brass.
-*[narrator] In Newark, I'm discovering,*
*elections are not about*
*media consults.*
*They're not about sound bites*
*or photo ops.*
*In Newark,*
*elections are won and lost*
*in the streets.*
♪ [music] ♪
[sirens wailing in the distance]
[cars whizzing by]
[telephone ringing]
- *[female voice] Cory Booker for mayor.*
- *[narrator] A few years ago,*
*I'd spent some time teaching in Newark.*
*So I was intrigued when I heard the buzz
about the election shaping up*
*between Booker and James.*
*They're both democrats.*
*Elections in Newark are non-partisan.*
*And people were saying*
*it would be a battle over the future of
Black leadership in America.*
*But no one was giving Cory*
*much of the chance.*
-We really--our focus is grassroots effort
so we try to skimp as much as we can
on a facility like this.
So--but we're basically looking at
is where we do all our scheduling,
all our fundraising operations
comes out of here.
[telephone ringing]
[machine running]
- *[Hiver Ambrose] This is what we live next door to.*
They're constantly making
black plastic bags.
*When we first moved in to that office,*
*it looked like this.*
[motor running]
- *[female voice] I have to write this thing,*
*it gets so loud here.*
*I gotta get out of here.*
- *[male voice] We're sort of plugging in*
*a surge protector to an outlet*
*to an extension cord to a surge protector*
*to sort of give electricity*
*to the whole place.*
- *That's pretty disgusting.*
[tap,tap,tap,tap]
- Oh!
- *[narrator] There's an old joke in Newark*
*that the only way an incumbent
ever leaves office is death or conviction.*
*But Cory thinks he's found another way.*
- *[Cory] I have a philosophy in campaigning,*
which is I walk every street
that I wanna represent.
All I've been doing in the evenings
is walking the streets
*and talking to people like you.*
I can't even see you,
I'm talking to a screen,
but I'll just let you know,
I'm running for mayor.
*- [male voice] Yeah.*
*- [Cory] And the reason why I'm running,*
Three reasons, real quick.
Okay?
*Newark faces real challenges,*
*we have murder rate is twice the Bronx.*
*We have almost a third of our people*
*living below the poverty line.*
*And we graduate only about 40%
of our kids from high school.*
*There's no excuse for this.*
*This city can be doing so much better*
*for the people that live here.*
- [kid] What were you doing?
- [Cory] I'm trying to get people
to vote for me.
You're gonna vote for me?
- [boy talking] Oh yeah! I wanna vote for you.
- [girl talking] What does vote mean?
- [Cory] You're gonna vote for me?
- [girl talking] What vote mean?
- [Cory] What does vote mean?
It means participating in democracy.
Trying to make your community better.
[Speaking in foreign language]
- Did I tell you my ancestors
come from a small island
to the south of Spain.
- [female] Oh, really?
- Yup, it's called Africa.
- Oh, small island.
[rain falling]
- [Cory] A little rain is not gonna stop us,
is it?
*-[female voice] Hell, no.*
- How you doing?
*- [female voice] Hi.*
What are you doing out this late?
- [female] It's just the case around here.
- It's almost 10 o'clock.
- *[narrator] Cory lives in Brick Towers.*
*A low-income housing project*
*in one of Newark's poorest wards.*
*It's the ward he represents*
*in the city council.*
*But he grew up 25 miles
and a world away.*
*In suburban Harrington Park, New Jersey.*
♪ [music] ♪
- *[Cory] My parents were very active*
*in civil rights movement.*
*And we integrated*
*in an all-white neighborhood.*
*After a big court fight
against a real estate agent,*
*who wouldn't show us
any houses there.*
*I was a high school*
*all-American football player.*
*Got a scholarship to play football*
*at Stanford University*
*where things really took off for me.*
*-[TV sportscaster] ...tight end,
Booker going straight, 15, 10, he'll score.*
*Touchdown Stanford.*
♪ [music] ♪
[cheering]
- *[Cory] To start my law school career,
I moved to Newark to set up a nonprofit*
*going after slumlords.*
But I got pulled into politics.
I decided to run for city council.
*And amazingly, we won.*
[lock clicking]
*After I got elected,*
*I moved in to Brick Towers,*
*because I wanted to stay close*
*to the community that elected me.*
*And every morning when I woke up*
*and when I came home at night,*
*I wanted to be reminded of the reasons*
*why I got into office into first place.*
- [male] How you doing, Mr. Booker?
- [Cory] Doing very well.
Are you gonna be alright?
- Yes, Sir. I'm gonna vote for you.
- Thank you very much!
- Definitely.
- Spread the word, alright?
- Yes, Sir!
- Alright.
- Hi! I don't want to interrupt your work.
- [female] My hands are wet.
- That's okay. I'll take a wet hand.
[Cory laughing]
- It's Cory, Cory Booker.
- [female] I've met you before.
- Okay.
- I like you, but I ain't voting for you.
- Tell me how you'll make a change
if you ever get in there.
- Well, if you keep putting
the same people in there,
you're not gonna see a change.
You're gonna get the same results.
- Yeah! But we've been hearing that
for so long.
- How old are you?
How old are you, brother?
- I'm 41 years old.
- Okay.
For the last 32 years of your life,
you've had the same leadership.
Sharpe James has been in the City Hall
since 1970.
We don't make change.
We let people get down there
and create dynasties.
We have the highest paid
city government in the country.
Your city council people
make over a hundred G's a year
when you put in all the perks.
Sharpe James got into office,
was making $70,000 a year in 1986.
He's raised his salary,
now he's making over $200,000 a year,
and he wasn’t satisfied.
*-[male voice] That's with Sharpe James?*
Yeah. Then he went over
and got another job.
He's got two jobs now.
We got brothers looking for one.
He's a Mayor and a State Senator,
makes about a quarter of a million dollars
a year.
So let's be for reals right now,
if every politician was on the streets,
okay?
Out there, really fighting
to make real solutions.
Okay?
Make every politician live
in the worst neighborhood in their city.
I guarantee,
the city would turn around a lot quicker.
[crown chattering]
- *[narrator] Today, Sharpe James
is formally throwing his hat into the ring.*
- [Sharpe James] This campaign,
from the beginning to the end,
has always been a positive campaign.
- *[male voice] I introduce myself*
*to the campaign's press person.*
*I tell him I'd love to spend some time*
*following the Mayor's campaign,*
*And he seems receptive.*
*I've never heard Sharpe James
speak before.*
*But once he takes the stage,*
*it becomes obvious*
*why he's never lost an election.*
♪ [music] ♪
[crowd cheering and clapping]
- *[Jim McGreevey] Thank you!*
Sharpe James is the real deal!
*Ladies and gentlemen!*
The Mayor and the next Mayor
of the great city of Newark,
Sharpe James!
[crowd shouting]
- *[Sharpe James] Today, is my wish*
*to continue to give something back*
to the city of Newark, that took
a poor boy,
living on the Howard Street
and South Orange Avenue,
in one room with a potbelly stove,
*with an outhouse in the backyard,*
one pair of sneakers,
one pair of pants,
*one t-shirt.*
And today, the poor boy
from Howard Street is your Mayor,
and seeking re-election.
[crowd shouting]
Let the work I've done speak for me.
I don't feel no ways tired.
[crowd shouting]
Today,
I officially declare myself
a candidate for re-election
as mayor
of the City of Newark, New jersey.
[crowd cheering]
- *[narrator] As I film the crowd,*
*the mayor notices me,*
*and says something*
*to his security detail.*
*Suddenly, I'm surrounded*
*by four plain-clothed policemen.*
-$$*[policeman] You have to be authorized
to come in here.$$*
-$$*[narrator] I was authorized.*$$
-*[male voice] Let's go.*
-$$*[policeman] I want to know who you
spoke to.$$*
$$*If not, I'm gonna have to lock you up.$$*
-That's fine.
-$$ I'm being for real with you.$$
$$That's why I'm not gonna ask you
if you could take the tape out.$$
-$$ I'm not gonna take the tape out.$$
-$$*[policeman] Open it, open it up.$$*
-$$*[narrator] No, I'm not gonna do that.$$*
-$$*[policeman] You're not?$$*
-$$*[policeman] You want to hang out
with me?$$*
-$$*[narrator] No, I don't want to do that
either.$$*
- $$Do you have identification on you?$$
-$$*[narrator] Are you a police officer?$$*
- $$ I sure am.$$
- $$*[narrator] Okay. Well we'll can talk about it
when we get outside.$$*
-Huh?
-*[narrator] We can talk about it when we go outside.*
- $$ Hmph! Follow me.$$
[crowd shouting]
-*[policeman] Out. Coming out.
Coming out.*
Where's your car, bro?
- *[narrator] I don't see what the problem is.
I spoke to them.*
-*[male voice] I don't see what the quest--
me either.*
$$*The Mayor said can you just just escort him out--*$$
- Come on.**
-*[narrator] I understand Okay, okay. *
-$$*[male voice] ...and that's the end of the question.$$*
*Let's go.*
-$$*[policeman] Hanging with Cory, huh?$$*
-$$*[narrator] I've been shooting Cory.$$*
$$*It's an election, and I'm trying
to cover the election.$$*
-$$*[policeman] He's not our guy.$$*
$$*I was gonna confiscate his film.$$*
-I need to see some identification.
- *[narrator] Can I see some identification
from any of you, police officer?*
- I sure am.
- *[narrator] Okay.*
*Okay. And so you need to see*
*identification of me, because why?*
- *[female officer] We are police officers
and we wanna see some identification*
*that's all we wanna see.*
-*[narrator] Okay.*
*And you're sure that you can just ask*
*people on the street for identification?*
- Sure, can.
- *[narrator] They write down
my home address and license plate number.*
[car door slams]
-*[narrator] I'm baffled.*
*I called the mayor's press person*
*and explain again what I'm doing.*
*He apologizes and says*
*he'll talk to the Mayor.*
*But my followup phone calls*
*and faxes go unanswered.*
*And I soon discover*
*that I'm not the only one having trouble
for spending too much time*
*with Cory Booker.*
- *[Jimmy Mitchell] I opened this place up
in '97.*
I never had any problem until
Cory Booker came to my house one night.
He wanted the people in the community
to get to know him, that didn't know him.
So, I suggested, I have a coffee klatsch
at my house,
invite 15 or 20 people over.
So I had one, one Sunday night.
Like I said, that Monday, police came,
said that I wasn't legal.
And they closed my business down.
-You can go to any place in the City,
and you can find a violation.
- *[narrator] Pablo Fonseca
used to be the Head of Code Enforcement *
*for the City of Newark.*
- If you're in this city,
you have be very careful.
you know, if you take on Sharpe James.
You know, everything is at his power.
It's at his behest.
He can make your life impossible.
[speaking foreign language]
- *[narrator] He was also Sharpe James'
campaign manager*
*in the Latino community.*
- [Pablo] Two years ago,
I supported a candidate
Sharpe James did not like
and did not back.
And even though I was protected
by civil service,
he brought me up on charges
and demoted me.
From supervising a four million dollar budget,
to supervising to people
in a sanitation garage.
That's a reality check on politics.
That's politics 101.
And it was, you know,
"WOW! What the hell!"
I sued the administration and won.
And I joined the Booker team.
- *[narrator] Jimmy Mitchell joined*
*the Booker campaign too.*
*As Cory's driver.*
*But for most people,*
*their businesses come first.*
- They sent Code Enforcement
down to Bergen street
*to basically threaten folks and they say,*
"If you put up a Cory Booker sign,
you'll facing consequences."
And having Code Enforcement
deliver that message,
you know, it's pretty persuasive.
- *[narrator] Over the next few weeks,*
*I meet a policeman
who's support for Booker*
*got him transferred to night patrol*
*in a dangerous neighborhood.*
*A minister who's church was threatened*
*by Code Enforcement,*
*after he criticized the Mayor.*
*A woman who fears she'll lose*
*her public housing,*
*if she hangs a Booker sign
in her window.*
- People have children.
People have houses and mortgages,
and rent to pay, and food to buy.
Why are you firing somebody
because they don't wanna vote for you?
That's their God-given right.
They're born in America,
you have the right to vote
for who you want to.
That's what it's all about.
And when you take that from somebody,
and the Lord doesn't stand up for it
and do something about it,
there's something seriously wrong.
- [Pablo] Just found this schedule,
like tonight's fundraiser,
it shouldn't have Jimmy Wright's
name on it.
Because if somebody picks this up,
God,
*Jimmy Wright's ass is gonna be at
cell block, 24 hours a day.*
- *[male voice] Right.*
- *[Pablo] These are like people*
*who are putting a lot on the line for us.*
That if Sharpe has any idea,
you know, he will crush these people.
[beep, beep, beep]
- Drug dealers don't own this city.
We do.
- I don't like that.
"Drug dealers don't own this city, we do."
-Drug dealers don't own this city.
We do.
- *[narrator] The polls show
that Cory's biggest challenge*
*is name recognition.*
*So he's outside his building,*
*trying to create a Booker brand.*
- [Hiver] I thought we're just bringing
a camcorder out.
-*[Cory] JUNIOR!*
-*[Junior] What do you want?*
- [Cory] Can I have
a cup of coffee, Junior?
- What you guys want?
I just woke up--another day.
- Okay. We got a shot here, Junior.
Tell me how I do.
-*[male voice] ACTION!*
-I'm Cory Booker. It's time that we put--
Ahhh!
I apologize.
-*[female] It's alright.
We'll take two.*
I apologize.
I'm Cory Booker. And I'm--
- [female] Okay. Here we go!
Quiet please!
[campaigning female voice playing on TV]
- *[narrator] Sharpe James
is pushing his story as well.*
*He grew up in Newark,*
*served in the army,*
*and taught gym at a local high school.*
*In 1970, at the age of 34,*
*he was elected to the City Council.*
*He served 16 years*
*and then running as a reformer.*
*He was elected mayor.*
*But in the 90's,
corruption scandals plagued his office.*
*Taking down his closest Aides
including his Chief of Police.*
*and his Chief of Staff, who was caught
with bags of money under the floorboards.*
*Sharpe weathered the storm though,*
*he was funny and an energetic booster
for the city.*
*New building went up in the downtown.*
*A performing arts center,*
*a minor league baseball stadium.*
*And Sharpe James gained a reputation*
*for creating a renaissance in Newark.*
- [shouting together] Five!
Four!
Three!
Two!
One!
Zero!
[rumbling sound]
[crowd cheering]
- *[Sharpe] This is a great day for Newark.*
We heard cheers when it came down.
Because what will go up
will be part of a new Newark.
And a new America.
*And new dreams and new hopes.*
- What the city is doing
is destroying home for low-income people,
and displacing them and not providing
places for them to live.
In the last 10 years,
10,200 homes have been destroyed,
and only 2500 homes have been replaced.
- [female] Cory Booker does not have
a vested interest in this city.
He doesn't own anything.
He's a Johnny-Come-Lately.
He doesn'’t understand the politics
of this town.
And just because you come in
and some golden boy,
and you happen to get lucky
and win one election,
does not mean that you'’ve got a handle
on what's going on.
People that live here
and have a vested interest in our city
know that Sharpe James is doing
a great job for this city.
-Sharpe James is trying to get credit
for something that he ain't even do,
he ain't nothing.
You know what I'm saying?
If he was right here?
I'll tell him in his face.
-Okay. Just don't blame this on Sharpe
because I know what's already here.
I don't know what I'm getting
if Booker gets in.
- Why you wanna blame it on Sharpe?
Cory's a councilman, if he can do it--
-...right in our neighborhood.
Sharpe James, Sharpe James,
what did Sharpe James do?
What did Sharpe James do?
-[shouting together] SHARPE! SHARPE!
-[together] BOOKER! BOOKER!
[beep, beep, beep]
[phone ringing]
- Yes! Mr. Simon?
This is Caroline Booker.
I'm the mother of Cory Booker.
- *[narrator] Cory's parents have come to town*
*for the rest of the campaign.*
The reason for my call is simply to thank you
for supporting Cory's campaign.
[laughing]
- *[narrator] I knew they had raised Cory
and his brother in a comfortable suburb.*
*So I was a little surprised*
*when I learned more about them.*
- *[Cory] My dad was born very poor*
*to a single parent in the south.*
You know, he had a tough, tough childhood.
I mean, you have to imagine
what it was like in '36 to be born
when they called it an illegitimate child.
*Really a self-made man*
*and really what I'm doing*
*is a result of my parents' guidance.*
A lot of people ask me,
"Who is this boy with a Rhode scholarship
and a Yale Law?"
"And why would he wanna come to Newark?"
My father grew up in North Carolina.
And he still has physical scars on his body
from being carved
by the White's Citizen Council
in that town for being
in the wrong side of town after dark.
In '61, the civil movement
started in North Carolina,
My father was one of the first
people on the stools
being kicked, bruised rib,
being hurt basically in that civil movement.
Back in the later 60s,
my parents were the first African-Americans
in the entire northeastern seaboard
to be hired by IBM.
My mom, was first.
My dad soon became the first
black salesman.
Has these awful stories about
making sales calls on people
and ripping up his cards,
saying, "You tell I.B.M. not to send
any more nigger salesman out here."
My parents told me, "To he who much is given,
much is expected."
And they expected their two children
to be a part of the struggle.
And I believe in my heart that
this Newark, New Jersey
and cities like it are frontiers
of the American dream.
And we as African-Americans
and we as Americans period,
have an obligation
to fight for our communities.
And that's why I'm doing this.
♪ [music playing] ♪
Hello everybody!
Happy Valentine's Day!
Unfortunately, I'm running today,
but I had to come through here
and spread some love.
We have some gifts to give out
to everybody down here.
- *[narrator] In Newark, giving stuff away*
*is a big part of campaigning.*
*There's a saying,*
*"If you feed them, you can lead them."*
*And candidates host chicken dinners,
charter buses to Atlantic City.*
*Give away flowers or perfume,*
*pot holders,*
*or tickets to concerts or the circus,*
*and it matters.*
*One woman told me
she wasn'’t gonna vote for Cory*
*because the Mother's Day card*
*that his office sent out last year*
*was cheap-looking compared to Sharpe's.*
*In his first few years in office,
Cory tried to defy that system,*
*But he's been getting more realistic.*
-So we'll set --
- [together] Sharpe's is this Saturday?
- What is he doing Saturday?
- He's doing bingo and breakfast.
- [Female 2] Bingo and breakfast.
- Sausage, home fries, eggs.
Our mistake in the last appearances
has not been to publicize
*that there's going to be major food.*
- Get the food, no brainer.
Let's do it.
-*[female] Okay.*
- Let's just feed--
-*[female] And entertainment, you're gonna..?*
- I'd rather win and owe
a hundred thousand dollars,
- *[female] Right.*
- than lose for not spending
a hundred thousand dollars.
- [female]Okay.
- And the check there,
is that from you or is that from...?
- *[narrator] Everyday,*
*Cory spends an hour or two*
*shaking down his friends,*
*and their friends.*
*And their friends.*
*People he knows from Stanford and Yale.*
*From Newark and New York*
*and California.*
*To be competitive,*
*they think they'll have to raise $15,000*
*every single day.*
- Show me the money.
Where's the money?
♪ [music] ♪
- *[female voice] Cash and check
made out to Friends of Cory Booker.*
- *[Cory] In our generation,*
I see that willingness
to make a sacrifice,
to make this nation
what it has not been yet.
To make it real for every single one
of it's citizen.
[crowd talking]
- [Cory] The things that we brag about,
buildings in the downtown,
they are symbols of a renaissance.
But not the substance of a renaissance.
*[Cory] David did beat Goliath.*
[crowd cheering]
- Okay?
I'll lead the upset to our poor Mayor.
And on May 14th, we, not me,
We! We! Are gonna upset Sharpe James.
[crowd shouting]
- *[narrator] It's Monday morning,*
*and everyone is talking about Sights.*
- *[Moses] We're the only nude club,
nude dancing club in Newark.*
- *[narrator] Last night, a Vice raid*
*looking for drugs and prostitution,*
*discovered a 16-year old stripper*
*working at the club.*
*They also found a young man
in line outside named Jermaine James.*
- The police department,
knowing who Jermaine James was,
told the mayor.
The mayor, what I understand,
told the police department
to issue a press release.
-Whoa!
-What is it?
[mumbling]
-Uh-oh.
-Whoa!
- *[Moses Wilson] Jermaine James,
turns out to be Cory Booker's Chief of Staff.*
- Oh my God!
I picked up my phone that morning,
I must've had 20 messages.
Just frustrated supporters.
Just angry.
What do we say?
And how do we move forward?
[man shouting]
-*[male voice] We got something.*
*We're gonna go off camera*
- Everybody want to go off camera.
- I'll be back in just a sec.
- *[narrator] It's a major blow to the campaign.*
*And they won't let me film the meeting
while they figure out what to do.*
*Sharpe James embellishes
the story a bit*
*and then hammers them with it*
*all over the city.*
- If any member of my staff
frequent a place of prostitution
and narcotics,
that's illegal in the City of Newark,
where 14 year olds are doing live sex act.
They don't have to touch of him,
I'm still gonna fire him!
[audience cheering and applauding]
- Sharpe did a mass mailing on it.
[bleep]
- Yeah, yeah.
- [bleep] [bleep]
- Everybody got it yesterday.
- *[narrator] What are you gonna do?*
- *[Pablo] Don't let it take over
the campaign.*
*We stick to the issues.*
*We don't talk about it.*
- *[narrator] Cory is a vegetarian.*
*He doesn'’t drink or smoke
and rarely even swears.*
*But one of the risks of running
a choir boy campaign*
*is that if you stumble, you fall hard.*
*As I spent more time in this city,*
*I found that there's a side of Newark
that most outsiders don't know about.*
*A Newark of homes with lawns,
of parks and middle-class neighborhoods.*
*And many Newarkers see*
*Sharpe's improvement downtown*
*as an expansion of that.*
- *[male] He's changed this town.*
*He's changed the preception of this town.*
And if you walk around this town
if you're from here, you can see it.
- It's gotten better everyday,
over the last 16 years.
And it's gonna get better tomorrow,
the next day after that.
It's getting better.
- *[narrator] It's clear that the Newark
of today is not the Newark of 1986*
*when Sharpe James took office.*
*But it's almost as if
there are two Newark's.*
*One, where thousands of people
struggle with relentless poverty*
*and crime*
*and poor schools year after year.*
*And another, where a proud phoenix*
*is rising from the ashes.*
*The questions is,*
*when voters go to the polls
in less than two months,*
*which Newark already thinking of?*
*I've continued calling*
*and faxing the mayor's office,*
*asking to spend time with him,*
*but no luck.*
*So I go to one of his public appearances*
*in the Portuguese district.*
- *[announcer] Everybody!*
*Let's welcome our mayor!*
*The great mayor of the City of Newark!*
*The honorable, Sharpe James!*
[crowd talking]
-[Sharpe] Hey partner?
-[female] Hello.
- [Sharpe] That's my date there.
How are you?
-[female] Okay.
- I get tired of people coming
to Newark,
moving their family here,
and then say,
"You know, Newark is so terrible,
you're gonna die."
"Your sky gonna fall out."
"You're gonna go in quicksand."
But they move here, why?
A political agenda.
Stop that nonsense.
We've been here during bad times!
Good time!
And we're gonna stay here
during improved time.
We ain't going nowhere.
And we don't need no carpetbaggars
coming here, telling us how bad we are.
Stay out!
It's a great day.
Don't let me get started.
Boy, I drank some of that wine,
they gave me some Porto wine.
I'm in trouble now.
Where is it?
They took it away from me.
I'm quitting.
There she is, Gayle told me,
"Stop talking now,
that wine is beginning to work."
"That Porto wine is too much."
Thank you very much.
Let's go to, bow wow.
- *[male voice] Mayor, look at this guy.*
- Who are you taking pictures for,
young man?
- $$*[narrator] I'm making a documentary.
We spoke before about it.$$*
- Isn't he the one before?
- This is Cory Booker man.
- Okay. Kill your film.
You film everybody else, but him.
-*[Sharpe] We don't want you filming.
I don't want you putting me on camera.*
- *[narrator] It's not about Cory.*
-*[male voice] Is it off?*
-$$*[Sharpe] Now, next time
we'll just take your camera.$$*
- *[narrator] It's a public event. It's a public--*
- Don't just film--film them.
But you're not gonna film him.
- *[narrator] He's the mayor of the city*
*and I'm allowed to film him.*
- Your not gonna film him.
- *[narrator] He's the mayor of the city*
*and I'm allowed to film him.*
- Your not gonna film him.
-*[narrator] Let go of my camera.*
- *[female voice] Please.Whoa.
You don't wanna do that.*
-*[narrator] Don't do that.
There's a lot of prints on that.*
- I'm just asking you not to film him.
- *[narrator] I'm allowed to film him.*
- He don’t want to be on your film.
- *It doesn't matter. He's the mayor of the city.*
[bell tolling]
- *[narrator] I've been having a lot of trouble.*
- Okay.
Still? Those guys?
-*[narrator] Yeah!*
*I mean, I've had like my camera*
*grabbed by a security people,*
*and stuffs like that.*
- I will try to talk to him, okay?
I mean, I've had to--I mean it's just not you.
The Ledger and The Times.
It's like I've had to go like--
and I mean, I know him too well.
I wish I'd started up
as soon as I could've gotten--
work up the rapport and--and--
and it's just idiotic.
It's also counterproductive.
I mean, it makes us looked terrible,
I think.
And the rest of us sees it. It's just...
- *[narrator] Right.*
- But these guys, I'll tell you.
I don't know who they are.
I can't believe it they got this thing
about the press.
It seems like a conspiracy.
It's so frustrating.
So I do have to try to grab him
and talk to him.
♪ [ music] ♪
- *[male voice] Experienced leadership!*
We don't want nobody practicing on Newark!
[cars honking]
*We need someone that knows*
*what's going on in Newark!*
We need someone that's been here
since 1967, right?
We need experienced leadership!
Experienced leadership!
[car honking]
- *[Rob Silva] It happened Saturday night after 10:30.*
*We had the police come out*
*and they dusted the whole window*
*for fingerprints.*
- I haven't seen the damage.
- *[Rob] Well, first thing
that happened was*
*Hive reached for the telephone
and there was no telephone.*
Felt the draft, walked back here,
saw everything opened up
and realized we've been broken into
and robbed.
*So they took the radio*
*Two telephones are ripped off the wall.*
But what's really bothering us is
they got two books worth of information.
*Two districts.*
*And they know*
*who's a Booker, who's a James,*
*who's undecided.*
*All that stuff.*
*And that's, you know,*
*it's a valuable sensitive of information.*
*We have it backed up,*
*but still they have it now.*
*One of the police officers
actually suggested that *
we have the whole trailer swept
for listening devices.
*Cory has somebody coming in to do that now.*
- *[narrator] Sweeping for bugs seemed*
*a bit paranoid to me,*
*until someone told me that
when Cory was first elected,*
*it was discovered that his home phone*
*was being tapped by the police.*
*The police insisted it was
an honest mistake,*
*but it still lingers
in the back of people's minds.*
*This morning, Sights is back in the news.*
- I'd heard that Sharpe James
said in his reelection speech,
that he would fire anyone in his staff,
who went to "places of ill repute,"
I think he called it.
And he was basically talking about Sights.
[people applauding]
- [Sharpe] I say we have to send a message
to our young people,
to our children, to our city
it is wrong to frequent houses of ill repute.
- You gotta have a lot of balls
to stand up with the governor,
State Senators,
Congressmen sitting behind you.
And make it sound as though
you've never been to a place
that you know you've been to.
Mayor Sharpe James sat right there
at a table, drinking Snapple,
watching, you know, a dancer on stage
dancing.
He was here himself.
- *[reporter] Were you in the club*
*or not in the club?*
- We are too smart to dignify that.
- Newark Mayor, Sharpe James, today
refused to answer repeated questions
about whether he visited a strip club.
*When a reporter asked him*
*if that was true today,*
*the Mayor lashed out.*
- Did I dismiss you?
Who do you think you yelling at?
-[reporter] Were you there?
-*Who do you think you're yelling at?*
Hey! Young man!
Who do you think you're yelling at
as a reporter?
Who you think you yelling at?
You better show some respect.
- Mayor James says that the only time
he went to club was when police raided it.
[phone ringing]
- You're here?
Let me show something here a bit.
You got, "It wasn't me."
[telephone ringing]
- In that club?
- What?
- He saying it wasn'’t him in that club?
- Yeah. Just read this.
- But did you see Channel 11 that night?
- Oh, when he got crazy?
- When he got up there,
and said that he was in there,
but to see what he could do about
closing it down.
[laughing]
- *[narrator] Sharpe James made a speech*
*at a barbecue he hosted*
*for a housing project last night.*
- Oh, yeah! And he called Cory last night, "Baby Face".
- *[male voice] Sharpe did?*
- Yeah!
Baby Face is a snake, don't trust him.
I was so mad.
I didn'’t know what in the world to do.
[woman mumbling]
-Yeah!
He had them all fooled last night.
[people talking]
-$$[female voice] Called Cory
a white Republican, yes he did.$$
-[male voice] You were there?
- Yeah, I live there.
- You heard him say it?
- Yes!
*That's what came out in the mail-room today,*
White Republican.
He gave that out last night to everybody.
- [male voice] Unbelievable.
- *[narrator] They brush aside
the Republican stuff*
*but the white comment stings.*
*And what it means to be black
is now becoming a major campaign issue*
*out in the streets.*
- The division, I mean--
and that's what I was telling people.
They were saying, "Oh, Cory's light skinned."
"Oh, he's almost white."
I'm like, this is what has kept us,
all this time, separated and divided
amongst ourselves.
*The racist comments that were coming*
*from the black people.*
An older lady walks up to my car and says,
"Who are you voting for?"
"The white man or the black man?"
I said, "I'm voting for Cory Booker."
They're mad at Cory,
because his mother was able
to give him a good education.
Because he wasn'’t raised in the projects?
So what?
You know, he's still black.
If my mother had the opportunity
to raise me in a better environment,
and give me a good education,
I'm sure she would have done that.
You know, but you can't be mad at him
because he's making it.
You can't be mad at him
because he has a vision.
You know what I'm saying?
You can't be mad at that.
You know, you had to just say,
"You know what? Let's make it so
all our children can be that way."
Why play a hate on him
because he's doing well?
Stupid!
It's just stupid. Really stupid.
- *[narrator] Sharpe is quoted calling Cory,*
"A faggot white boy".
*And telling audiences*
*that he takes money from the Ku Klux Klan.*
*On the* Today Show,
*he says that Cory,*
*a Baptist, is actually Jewish.*
- *[Sharpe] He went to Stanford
and he's Jewish.*
He tells a story about his graduation,
where he couldn'’t date a white girl.
- *He also says of Cory,*
*"You have to learn to be African-American.
And we don’t have time to train you."*
*And all of this is just*
*when he's speaking on the record.*
- We ask our black children get educated
and they do and we call them White.**
That's sad.
It's truly sad.
And to believe that,
it's not that Sharpe did that,
that's dirty, that's low.
Sharpe is a low individual.
For them to believe it?
And they're talking about civil rights?
These are people who have been through--
some of them have been through the 60s.
That's a disgrace to Martin Luther King,
to Malcolm X,
to
And anybody and everybody who worked
like a demon to get us beyond that.
- And this is an attempt.
A really sad attempt by Sharpe James
to racialize his campaign.
And ignore--distract people
from what the real issues are,
safety, security, economic empowerment,
and good schools.
The truth to the matter is
I'm an African American
who's benefited from the
legacy of struggle in our country.
I'm an African-American who benefited
from my parents' generation
who marched for me,
who sat in for me,
literally bled that southern soil
red for me.
I have been told by my family
never to forget where you came from
and the struggles
that got you to where you are.
And my grandfather who passed away
during this election,
the day I got my diploma from
Yale Law school,
grabbed me by the arm and said,
"Don’t you ever forget that the diploma
you are holding was paid for
in the blood, sweat and tears of your ancestors.
And if you wanna prove worthy
of that struggle,
then you must continue it.
If you wanna be proved worthy
of that legacy,
then you must roll up your sleeves
and get to work.
We're gonna make the changes, alright?
Thanks, guys. God Bless you.
My voice is shot.
- *[narrator] Cory is spending
more hours everyday knocking on doors.*
- Oh, watch your head, watch your head,
don't hit your head.
Oh! You hit your head.
What's up big man?
-[kid] Fine.
- He promised that he can help mommy
get a job so we can get out of here.
What we're gonna do is
we're gonna definitely fight
to help people get more employment.
- We're gonna win this campaign
in the streets.
We're not gonna win this campaign
on T.V.
on radio.
We're gonna win this campaign in the streets.
- [announcer] Good morning
Ladies and gentlemen!
Let's get ready to rumble!
[crowd shouting]
IT'S TIME FOR CHANGE!
- *[narrator] The crowds at campaign events*
*is getting bigger and bigger.*
- [Cory] Now it's time that we pull together.
Black Newarker.
White Newarker.
Portuguese.
Brazilian.
*Puerto Rican.*
Old.
Young.
We need to be unified
because in unity give is strength.
There's an old African saying that says,
"Sticks in a bundle can't be broken."
[crowd cheering]
- *[narrator] But the bigger the rally,*
*the bigger the bill.*
*And everything requires more fundraising.*
[car door slamming shut]
[crowd talking]
- You ain't seen this room?
Let me show you this room.
- *[Hiver] It's been described to me as*
The Card Room.
Can you step in here Mr. Booker.
-You can step in Mr. Booker.
- Can you imagine playing with
with three of your friends?
- In here?
- In here.
- Sure.
- Certain nights though.
- Sure, you wanna play some cards?
- Yeah.
- Roll the dice?
-*[Cory] The people on this town
really have amazed me.*
And maybe you realize more
than any other place
the truth of what
Martin Luther King said that,
"We are all caught in
an inescapable network of mutuality,
*tied in a common garment of destiny."*
That, "Injustice anywhere
is a threat to justice everywhere."
- [Cory] Jimmy?
- Yes, sir?
- *[Cory] There are rich people in this world.*
- You're telling me.
- *[Cory] They live in some very large houses.*
- *[Hiver] I had to call my--
when I flushed the toilet*
*and it didn'’t make any noise?*
[male laughing]
- *[Cory] Left. I'm sorry.
This way, this way.*
- *[Hiver] I said I got to call my girlfriend
and tell her about this.*
[male laughing]
- *[Cory] What did Job say?*
*"Naked I came in to the world...*
-*[narrator] Naked I came in to the world naked.*
*And naked I shall leave.*
-*[male voice] Does your toilet
make a sound?"*
[Cory laughing]
-[female voice] *Hey there, Cory!"*
-[Cory] I did really well.
- *[male voice] Hey, did you see
the total for today?*
- What was the total for today?
- *[male] Sixty four.*
- *[narrator] That's $64,000.*
*for the day.*
- *[Cory] Pretty damn good.*
- *[narrator] Cory's fundraising efforts
has managed to surpass Sharpe's.*
*Their filings with the government
showed that *
*each side has raised between two
and a half and three million dollars,*
*which should be a huge boost for Cory.*
*It shows that he's a real competitor.*
*But Sharpe has managed to turn*
*this advantage into a disadvantage.*
*Everywhere he goes,*
*He's saying that Cory has raised*
*10 million dollars, not three.*
*And he's trying to buy the election.*
- Ten Million dollars can buy a lot of votes.
Why does Cory Booker, after four years
in Newark, have 10 million dollars?
If money can buy an election,
then it will.
But what the people is saying in Newark,
- [together] Newark is not for sale!
- Booker can't buy this.
- *[male voice] Not for Sale!*
- [together] Newark is not for sale!
- [Cory] Well, Sharpe has this amazing ability
to tell a lie so many times,
that people believes that it is the truth.
*If the mayor of city is saying this,*
you're threatening to put some here.
- *[narrator] Even I began to wonder whether
perhaps I was being spun*
*by the Booker folks.*
*So I confirmed by looking online.*
*It's all public information
on a government website.*
- [Cory] So we don't have 10 million dollars?
- *[narrator] But it's not just a matter of*
*how much money there is.*
*It's also where it comes from.*
*An anonymous flyer goes out,*
*accusing Cory of conspiring with Jews
to take over the city.*
*Sharpe tells reporters that Cory is
propped up by white right-wing investors.*
- Because of the extreme root for white
right-wing Republican party
who is supporting him.
- *[narrator] His commercials and speeches
and mailings*
*all push the message hard.*
- [Cory] I'm a tool for the Republic Party.
I confess it.
- [Jen] I thought you were a tool of the Jews.
- I'm a tool of the Jews, the Republican party,
Afghanistan, the Taliban.
[laughing]
I am a member of the KKK.
I'm part of the CIA conspiracy.
- Oh, you wanna know what
the newest one is?
- [Cory] What?
- You know what the newest one is?
- I'm gay?
-There's a media conspiracy
to elect Cory Booker.
- I'm part of the media conspiracy.
♪ [music] ♪
- *[DJ] You're all listening to*
*98.7 Kiss WRKS FM New York.*
And our guest, candidate for mayor
of the city of Newark, New Jersey,
Cory Booker.
He says he's a Democrat.
*No matter what some of these people*
*are saying about him including his opponent,*
*Sharpe James.*
*This piece that we have here from the internet*
*The Black Commentator, rips you a new booty.*
[Cory laughing]
- *[DJ 2] What is this dalliance with Republicans?*
That you know of course,
you say the word, "Republican"
and black voters are ready to run.
- [Cory] Well, let's just put it this way.
I'm a Democrat.
If there are some moderate Republicans
who have chosen to support me,
*that's their prerogative.*
What my focus has been since
I've been a young man,
is working to make sure
the Democratic Party
is as strong as it can be,
*so that the needs of*
*inner city communities are met.*
So I'm proud of my root
in the Democrat Party.
And I'm tired, frankly, of Sharpe James
trying to cast this debate
in terms of Republican and Democrat
as opposed to what he should be casting
in terms is,
why does his city have a poverty rate
that's going up?
Why is his city have an unemployment rate going up?
- But do you think it's spoken now
to align yourself with extremist
or far right people like J.C. Watts?
I mean, you know...
- I'm sorry. I'm not sure
what you're talking about.
- Hold on a second--
- I've never met J.C. Watts.
- Alright.
- Nor have aligned myself with him.
- Listen, I mean, you have had no sort
of alliances with them?
- None, whatsoever.
- Sort of the Republican handlers,
anybody coming to you, "I wanna bring you..."
- These smear campaigns really concern me
because I've never met J.C. Watts.
I've never met a lot of the people
he's talking about.
I've been a lifelong Democrat.
And suddenly, here we are,
wasting time talking about
Sharpe James' accusations.
- Here's the problem though, Cory,
and I think that people are confusing
your broad-based support,
I mean, I gather, just from looking
at the contributors
and looking where the money's coming from,
you're getting a broad base of support.
And you know what, Cory?
That scares people.
- Well, let me tell you this,
this is what is almost comical about this,
the majority of Sharpe James' supporters
are developers
and people that have city contracts.
And the majority of those are people
that don’'t live in the city of Newark.
And the majority of those happen
to be white.
- *[DJ 2] Republicans?*
- Many of them are Republicans as well.
So, here's a man, who is allowing our city,
the most the precious resource that we have,
our 600 million dollar budget,
87% of those contracts are being taken
by outsiders.
- *[DJ] And we will be right back
with our guest, Cory Booker.*
A Democratic candidate for mayor
of the city of Newark, New Jersey,
after these messages.
[recording] You're listening to the Week in Review on Kiss.
- I'm enjoying this.
- My brother.
[laughing]
- I was...
- *We knew you can handle it.*
- Now I’m waking up. Before, I wasn’t awake
- *[Radio DJ] Look, I've given Cory a hard time*
*because I have some questions.*
*And I was suspicious about his associations.*
*But I think that it's time for a change.*
*Cory Booker, to me,*
*represents a type of young leadership,*
*a leadership that Newark wants.*
*I like his answers in the questions of*
*police, what he's gonna do with that.*
*I like his answers in the question*
*of education.*
*I think he has bright ideas.*
*And I think that's what Sharpe James
is afraid of.*
[crowd applauding]
- Today, I'm endorsing
Cory Booker for mayor of Newark,
because I believe he is Newark's best hope
for the future.
Cory represents the best of the
Democratic Party,
honored by both the DNC and the DLC
and asked to speak at the
Democratic National Convention.
So if anyone tells you Cory Booker
is not a Democrat,
they got a lot of people they got to argue with.
[crowd applause]
[Foot steps echoeing]
- [female] We're really tired of
people lying to us and telling us,
"We're gonna do this.
If you elect me, I'm gonna do this."
And then you get into office
and you work part-time
and you don'’t do what you say you're gonna do
And then our streets still look like they look,
and stolen cars
and drugs
and we don'’t have what we need.
We're tired.
- *[Cory] I need your help.*
- We're really, really tired.
- *I need your help.*
All I ask you is to look at me
and how I've led my fight.
- Okay.
- Okay?
- *See, I don’'t listen to that stuff
because I'’m not into politics*
*and I haven'’t been in New Jersey that long.*
- *Give me two minutes.*
- But they'’ve been following you
and now they'’re disappointed at the fact
that some of the things
that you have promised that you have not done--
- *Specifically what?*
- Okay. You said you live in Brick Towers.
There is not proof that you have lived
in Brick Towers.
- *Oh my God!*
Oh my God!
-*[woman] I don’t know.*
- Stop for a second. Stop for a second.
Stop for a second. Hold up.
I appreciate you keeping it real with me
about what you've heard out there
*what people are saying,*
but I'm simply saying, I'm asking you
to look at my record.
And if you want to right now,
anybody doesn'’t think I live in Brick Towers,
come to my apartment, I'll show you my mess.
I got dishes in the sink,
*I got dirty laundry on my floor.*
People say, "I'm tired of politicians
lying to them."
That’'s because we’'ve had the same politicians there for 32 years.
Thirty-two years.
- It's just sad that, you know,
we'’ve been lied to for so long.
- You have a question for me, brother?
Okay. Fire away.
- [kid] Is you lying?
*[audience member] Thank you.*
[laughter]
- [Cory] That crushes me, man.
- [Jimmy] That Hurts.
I mean, all the time you put in, man.
- *[narrator] New numbers have just come in
from a campaigns pollster.*
[dialing beep, beep, beep]
- Hey, Jeff. It's Van and Cory.
-*[Jeff] Hi.*
- *[narrator] The poll shows *
*the mayor is still ahead, 41% to 33.*
- [Van] Hello!
- *[narrator] But that leaves 26% of Newark*
*still undecided.*
- 41-33, what does that mean?
- Well--
- Is that good for him or bad for him?
-$$*[male voice] Bad for him but
we have to make it fatal for him.$$*
-$$ *Actually Jeff, wouldn't you say
it's almost ...$$*
$$*Generally speaking , if this were a normal race,$$*
$$*wouldn't you can say,
an incumbent at 41,$$*
$$*is in extreme trouble, right?$$*
-$$*[Jeff] Yes.$$*
- Really? So they're in trouble?
-$$ *But it isn't a not normal race.$$*
-$$*How do we drive is favorables down?$$*
-$$*[male voice] A negative attack, I think, Jeff?*$$ **
-$$*[Jeff] Yeah. Negatives will drive
his numbers down* $$
$$*and they will also drive our own down.$$*
$$*And Cory, it's not gonna be pretty.$$*
-*[narrator] It's a tricky balance.*
*In the past, when Cory ads*
*have pointed to crime or failing schools,*
*Sharpe spun them as an attack*
*on the city itself.*
*If they criticize the mayor directly,
there's a risk of it backfiring.*
- The thing about Sharpe James
that you have to remember is that,
he is 66 years old,
32 of those years,
almost half his life were spent
in public office.
*And people have been grown with him.*
*People know him.*
*People like him.*
*He's a good cheerleader for the city.*
-[Sharpe] One of the best basketball teams in
in America.
- *[Van] People vote for Sharpe*
*because they like Sharpe.*
*I mean, Sharpe James is their guy.*
And I mean, same thing happened in
Washington D.C. with Marion Barry.
I mean, how's a guy who gets busted
for what he's busted with get re-elected?
And essentially, people begin
to feel defensive about,
either folks from the outside
or other people going after
somebody who they felt is their guy.
- [Cory] Is this going to damage--I mean,
I had two seniors today tell me
they were really respected the way
I was running this campaign
and not running a negative campaign
like Sharpe is--yada-yada-yada.
So, now, I wanna make sure
we don’t have a backlash as a result of this
with a candidate who 70%
of the people in city say they like.
-$$*You know, I care less than you do
about how people are gonna feel at the end.$$*
$$*I'm more concerned about winning
the election.$$*
- You're call. I'm not gonna lose this race
because we're afraid to punch Sharpe
in the nose.
I just think that there's a way to do it with dignity.
-*[male voice] Right.*
-That you're still rolling up the sleeve
and slugging this guy in the face.
But there's a way to do it with dignity.
-*[Male TV announcer] Sharpe James says
he's the real deal.*
*The truth is, Sharpe James is getting
really rich at the taxpayer's expense.*
*While schools crumble and crime and drugs
plague our streets,*
*James has given himself a raise
to over $200,000 a year.*
*He bought two vacation homes,
a 46 foot yacht and a Rolls Royce.*
*The real deal?
How 'bout a great deal...*
*For Sharpe James.*
*After 16 years, it's time for a change.*
♪ [music playing] ♪
-We're gonna vote for you, Sharpe James.
-This is unlike any election--
this is unlike the election I usually work on.
Most elections I worked on are like,
you know, media, advertising, polling
all that kind of stuff, you know?
And this really is more
old-fashioned political machines.
You know, my parents were like
this in Boston, when they were there.
And you know what, with all the stuff that
go on street level politics up here,
you know, it definitely is a throwback.
- *[Pablo] You know what happened
to the rally at the North ward? Tonight?*
- *[male voice] Yeah, The Flamboyan.*
- He's just closed the place down.
- What?!
- Yeah.
- What do you mean he closed it down?
- The place is closed for business.
- *I go to the club down the street
to try to move it*
*from this place to the other place.*
*The guy goes, "Listen Pablo, I love you
but I'm too afraid to let Cory in here.*
He goes, "You know, Pablo,
you know how politics is,
if I let Cory in here,
I'll have the police here tomorrow.
You know, they'’ve been laying off of me
since I let the mayor put his signs up here,
the police don'’t come anymore.
Yep. You know Sharpe,
that's what he does, he threatens everybody.
- [Pablo] Just paranoia. Totally, totally
paranoia.
It's unbelievable.
- [Cory] This campaign of intimidation is
not gonna win it for them.
It's just not gonna win from them.
-[Pablo] Somebody put a thread in the e-mail.
- [Cory] What did they say?
- [Pablo] Cory Booker, better watch out.
I'm trying to get it.
- [Cory] Was it a physical threat?
- [Pablo] Yeah.
- *[narrator] The heat is being turned up*
*even hotter on business owners.*
*And some asked the campaign to come*
*and take back their Booker signs.*
- *Think about it this way, if Cory wins,
you don't have a problem.*
- But if you don’t, I have big problem.
[crowd talking]
- You wanna put the little one
on the end of the street?
We'll take the big one back?
I know you're not gonna put it up,
you're worried, I understand that.
That's fine.
- [male voice] You know,
people are getting closed down, you know?
- *[lady] See, our only thing is*
*we have city contracts.*
*He told the Police Officers
they're not allowed to go to any more*
*Cory Booker fundraisers.*
- *[narrator] They're also being encouraged*
*to donate money to the James' campaign.*
- *And this cop came down*
*and it's like you know,*
*since you have the contract*
*for the city of Newark*
I said, "Yo man, I can't afford it,
here's 250."
I don’t understand.
They'll do you in, man.
They will do you in.
There's no way around it.
♪ [music] ♪
- I mean, see what they're doing?
- Yeah, I know, I saw that.
- Yeah, they're ripping down
tons of our signs.
They took 200 signs in the North Ward.
The wall signs.
- *Two hundred?*
- Two hundred wall signs.
[Booker campaign staff talking]
- *[narrator] Tension is rising on the campaign.*
*And it seems like as much effort*
*as people were spending before*
*on winning over voters,*
*They're now spending just trying*
*to keep the election honest.*
- I got a very interesting call,
an anonymous call from my cell phone
early this week.
And this person told me that
there are three machines in the East Ward,
that she believes are being tampered with.
Okay. I asked her specifically
what are the machines
But she said that,
"I really can't tell you that
because of the position that I'm in.
They would know how you got
the information."
I was inclined to think that
she was calling from the board of election.
- Remember that this is not a debate.
It's not an intellectual debate.
It's not an academic debate.
You will not win any points
for the quality of your arguments, for the logic--
- It's saying things that will resonate with the crowd.
- Right. So you really wanna think now
of some good snappy sound bites.
Even though I know that sounds like
just memorize them and see
if you can throw them in there.
- Okay.
Some of the document, like the tax rate,
I wanna be able to hit him on that.
Charging them raised tax 100%.
Raised it from da-da-da to da-da-da.
- *[Jen] Don't da-da-da. Sharpe raised it 110%.*
-Alright.
- *[Jen] Because people-- the thing about a debate is
people believe what you say.*
- Right.
- *[Jen] So you don’t need to offer them*
*much evidence.*
- Alright.
- *[Jen] Sharpe James has raised taxes 100%,*
versus, Sharpe James has raised taxes 100%
from blah-blah-blah to blah-blah-blah.
- *[Cory] I see what you're saying,
let's give these two numbers--*
- What numbers?
- The tax--what the tax rate was back in '96,
what it is now, with an average family pay,
with what an average family pays now.
- Just one Sharpe.
- Okay.
- Promise me you won't say--
- I will not promise you I won't say that.
I'm good at reading audiences.
- You don’'t have an audience.
- I'm gonna go with the flow.
- Alright but hear me, because first of all,
you have no audience.
The audience is one camera.
- No. When I need to think on my toes.
And I need to make a come back.
If Sharpe keeps going back to the things,
I wanna know my shit.
- Okay.
- So...
- But just keep in mind...
- I'm not gonna promise you anything.
You've given me some good things,
some good pointers but ultimately,
it's me out there.
I have to go with my guts.
- I know that.
But the one thing that I know
*is that if you roll out something*
*that takes longer than a minute,*
*they will cut you off*
*and then your point will be lost.*
- I understand that.
- *[Jen] Okay?*
- I understand the point.
Just make sure I get that information.
[Door slamming shut]
-$$*[Jen] He's gonna boff it.$$*
$$*He's gonna try and do his thing
and he's clearly gonna boff it.$$*
- [narrator] I show up at the debate
with my camera
*but the police told me I can't film it.*
*I put the camera on my bag,
but continue recording audio.*
-$$*[Cory] I'm a black man,$$*
$$*and I'm insulted that another black man
would come up here$$*
$$*and try to accuse me of
being something other.$$*
*[narrator] As soon as it ends,
a fracas breaks out.*
*The mayor accuses a Booker's supporter
of being a terrorist.*
-$$*[Sharpe] He frightened me--he's a terrorist.$$*
$$*Get his Identification please.$$*
*-[narrator] They haul the man into another room.*
-$$*[Polceman] Why do you want him?$$*
-$$*[Sharpe] You wanna find out,
check him out.$$*
-*[narrator] Two lawyers from the Booker
campaign argue until he's released.*
-$$*[male lawyer] Why is he being held?*$$
**
-$$*[female lawyer] Why is he being detained?$$*
-$$*[policewoman] Everybody step back.
Everybody step back.$$*
-*[narrator] The mayor lunges at the lawyers*
*but his supports hold them back.*
-$$*[Sharpe supporters] Sharpe! Sharpe!$$*
-$$*[Sharpe] Where you going?$$*
-$$ Come on...$$
-*[narrator] A booker supporter taunts him.*
-$$*[Booker Supporter] See you
in two weeks!$$*
-$$*[James Supporter] See YOU in two weeks!
I'll see you in a little while...$$*
$$*See you later!
See ya!* $$
$$Faggot!$$
$$Carpetbaggers!$$**
-$$*[female James Supporter] See,
Carpetbaggers!$$*
-$$*See YOU in two weeks.$$*
-$$*[James Supporter] Don't get caught
in the streets!$$*
$$*Don't get caught in the streets!$$*
-*[narrator] Everyone pours out onto the sidewalk.*
*As I take out my camera,*
*A policeman from the mayor's security team*
*comes at me.*
Let go of my camera!
Free press! This is America!
This is America!
-$$*[Policewoman] This is private property.$$*
-$$ This is a sidewalk.
It is not private property.$$
$$This is a sidewalk.$$
-*[narrator] He's broken the microphone off*
*of my camera,*
*while the mayor is whisked away.*
*Reporters gather around.*
- I was trying to listen to what
the mayor were saying.
And I happen to have shades on.
So when he commented about the shades,
I took them off.
So after I took them off, he say,
"He's still a terrorist.
Run a check on him. See who he is,
I don't know him.
He's not a Newark residence."
So I pulled out my Newark Welfare ID.
So they said, "Where's your address?"
I said, "I gave my address," right?
My social security number
was on there and everything.
They said that wasn't sufficient enough.
They wanna take me out to the side.
I told them I was there with Cory Booker.
That's when they really took me out.
I was just sitting there.
No. I was just sitting there.
-He was just looking.
He was just looking.
-Like he said.
This is what he saw,
he saw the hat.
- *[reporter] Alright.*
- You know what I'm saying?
That's all it was.
He saw the hat.
- You saw how I comported myself
and I really hope again
that you'll write the truth.
This is how Cory behaved.
This is how Sharpe James behaved.
- *[narrator] The Booker team is struggling*
*to get the press to more outrage.*
*But so much of the reporting*
*just treats the election like a sport.*
*They call it* rough-and-tumble politics.
*As if Newark were a crazy regime*
*on the other side of the globe.*
*Rather than an American city,*
*just 12 miles from Manhattan.*
- He's doing some things,
I don’t understand how he gets away with it.
You couldn’t do that in New York.
- *[narrator] I realized that I've gotten*
*a bit out of my league.*
*If a cop will shove me*
*and break my camera in broad daylight,*
*with reporters around,*
*what would happen if, as they taunted,*
*I am caught out in the streets?*
*Two different reporters
who cover Newark take me aside,*
*and tell me to be very careful.*
*I ask one Booker aid if this is serious.*
*If I should be worried.*
*Or it is really just*
*rough-and-tumble politics.*
*He tells me that the night before last,*
*his front door was smashed in.*
*And now he's carrying a gun in his car.*
[Thud, thud, thud]
- I have not been sleeping that easily
for the last year or two.
So it's another __ five o'clock
in the morning and can't get back to sleep.
That's City Hall,
and me and Mayor Sharpe James.
*He stopped shaking my hand months ago.*
- Good afternoon!
I'm Chris Christie,
the United States attorney
for the district of New Jersey.
Today, I have directed attorneys,
investigators and other staff in my office
to be prepared to serve as induction of servers
of the Newark Municipal Elections
*Tuesday, May 14th.*
- I'm very happy that now
we have every assurance,
every possible assurance that
this is gonna be elections that's safe,
fair and the democracy will be served.
-*[Female announcer] Sharpe James.*
*Let's continue the progress.*
*Vote Sharpe James*
*Vote for the right person*
[man shouting]
- *[narrator] Back-to-back, *The Star Ledger,*
New Jersey's largest newspaper*
*and the *New York Times
*have endorsed Booker.*
- [Pablo] Awesome, awesome article.
- *And suddenly this local election,*
*in a medium-sized city,*
*has become the center
of American Black politics.*
- This is the director, Spike Lee,
asking you to do the right thing
by voting for Cory Booker
for Newark Mayor, this Tuesday, May 14th.
[TV New Clips]
- *[male voice] This has clearly been the most
exciting election in recent years.*
- *[female voice] Both candidates
have alleged acts of intimidation*
*and other shenanigans*
*throughout this race.*
*The campaign, at times intense,*
*has attracted the interest*
*of the national media.*
- *[narrator] Sharpe has been lobbying
Bill Clinton for an endorsement.*
*And he says in a speech,*
*that the former president
will be coming to stump for him.*
*But the next day,*
*Clinton's office says*
*he won't be taking sides.*
*Sharpe sends out a mailing*
*featuring Clinton, anyway.*
*That implies the endorsement*
*without being explicit enough
to get him in trouble.*
- *[Cory] How long though was
this picture anyway?*
- *I think it's three years ago.*
- *Jesse Jackson comes to town
and calls Cory, "A wolf from sheep's clothing."*
- [Cornel West] This is not just about Newark now.
This is about the nation.
What you are beholding here is a new vision,
That's what we're talking about
here in Newark.
[crowd applause]
- This is just the beginning for you, man.
I'm serious.
- I appreciate that.
-You got, five, ten, fifteen years...
-But this the real battle for America
right here.
This is the front line of the American Dream.
- *[narrator] But as people lined up to get
Cornel West to autograph his book*
*on race relations in America,*
*a sound truck rolls by.*
-$$[recorded announcement] You ain't black!$$
$$You're suspect, boy. You ain't black.$$
$$You're suspect boy.$$
$$You're suspect.$$
- I don’t know. I have no idea.
Yeah, I'm in front of the TV right now
waiting for the poll results.
-*[News on TV] There's an incredibly close race
emerging for the next mayor of Newark.*
*According to the new Eyewitness news poll,
incumbent mayor, Sharpe James,*
*now finds himself in a statistical dead heat--*
[crowd shouting]
- We're in the fight!
We're in a fight.
- It's only costing fucking $200,000
a week, but you know...
That's a great poll for us,
that is an awesome poll for us.
Everybody who's with Sharpe right now
has gotta be thinking twice.
Cory Booker!
- [Cory] How you doing, ladies?
-[together] Fine.
Sure?
-[girl] Yes.
Who are you gonna vote for, for Mayor?
- *[girl] You.*
- Thank you!
- *Mommy, mommy it's Cory Booker!*
- [Cory] How are you?
Let's go, let's go.
Watch the cars.
Hey, how are all of you doing?
- *[male] How are doing, Mr. Booker?*
- Doing very well.
- My name is Malcolm McDonald,
and I just met Cory Booker, my best friend.
- If you don’t believe me, smell my hands.
- *[narrator] Smell your hands?*
*What do you mean?*
- Yes. Because I just touched Cory Booker.
- *[narrator] And he's got a smell?*
- Uh-huh.
- *[narrator] What does he smell like?*
- And she loves him.
- He smells like the future.
- Night before, the evening before the battle.
I feel good.
I feel really good.
We fought a great fight.
And tomorrow is his execution.
And prayer.
Life can change a lot for all of us
come the end of the day.
You know, who knows what
the outcome can be?
I could be completely wrong.
I could have completely underestimated
our enemy.
And he could just come out and crush us
or keep us and go--
We can narrowly lose.
My gut, if guts tells me that
we got this guy against the ropes
and he's gonna go down tomorrow.
[Siren wailing]
♪ [music] ♪
- *[narrator] It's Election Day.*
[crowd shouting]
-*[TV clip] [Sharpe] Democracy.*
-*[New announcer] Sharpe James knows
more than any other *
*that you need to get out the voters
on election day.*
*In tight races like this,
it could make the difference in the end.*
- *[narrator] Each campaign
has around 1500 workers on the streets,*
*dragging people out to vote,*
*waving signs,*
*and watching the polls for cheating.*
*With the voter turnout that's expected,*
*it works out to around one worker*
*for every 15 votes.*
*Some of the workers are volunteers.*
*But many of them are paid.*
*And both campaigns are spending*
*hundreds of thousands of dollars today.*
*Since Sharpe won't let me get close,*
*I have another camera crew cover him.*
- *[male] This is Michael Tucker.*
$$ *Micheal, this is our mayor.$$*
$$Mike is in charge
of the three buses.$$
$$ All these people come
from Pennsylvania.$$
$$ We work with Mike every year.$$
- Time to tell the truth
now, your on candid camera.
-$$ We're from Philadelphia
and don't have a clue.$$
$$ We're just here to help out.$$
-$$ For who? Who are we showing
our support for?$$
-$$ Oh yeah, James.
James the real deal. $$
-Why we came from Philly?
To get paid.
- Well, they can come here.
The press can come here.
I can stand here while talking to a guy.
- This is a volunteer army
against the paid army.
And a volunteer army
So I'm indebted to the people of Newark
who are coming out,
pouring out their love of their city,
love of people.
Volunteers, you can't pay volunteers.
They're doing it because they love this city.
They live here, and they love this city.
- [male] Sharpe James the real deal!
Sharpe James the real deal!
-We're much better than we were before
in the city.
[crowd shouting]
-...community? He don't give a fuck
about our community. Nothing.
-If you want us to go beyond?
Well, we'll take it beyond.
- [female] ...Wilson Avenue school
allegedly broken,
poll workers are claiming that
they have no emergency ballots to go to.
- *[narrator] Problems are erupting all over the city.*
*Lawyers and poll challengers*
*race around putting out fires.*
*But new ones spring up in their place.*
-$$*[male voice] All right, we just got another
report that now$$*
$$*there's a power outage.
They've disconnected the power.$$*
$$*If you can get someone over there,
I'd greatly appreciate it.$$*
Okay? Thanks.
US attorney's office finally getting back to me.
- Intimidation? High intimidation
in all the poll districts.
- [Pablo] We've had machine broken
and we've had levers broken.
We've had district leaders
bringing in people to vote.
Yeah, it's the same politics as usual.
-*[TV announcer] At this polling station, *
*Booker's campaign complained
that elderly residents*
*were bringing people into
the polling booths with them.*
- Have you ever had a day
when Mr. Booker didn’'t make an accusation?
Have you ever had a day
when he didn'’t complain?
Have you’ ever had a day when
he didn'’t condemn everyone
and everything to spin the media?
- A new day is dawning in Newark.
The sun is rising on new opportunities
and new hopes.
Today is a glorious day in our city.
- *[narrator] But as the day goes on,*
*the relative inexperienced
of Cory's operation starts to show.*
- They're seeing in a lot of places
where we need more poll workers.
But we don’t have more bodies,
you have bodies down there?
- I don’t know what to do, what I'm suppose to do.
I couldn't just go out to the polling places.
What is my job?
What am I supposed to be doing?
- The police is down at 505 Mount Prospect,
ripping down our signs.
- *[narrator] A Federal judge has ordered*
*the city government*
*not to selectively take down any Booker signs.*
*But around the city,
the federal order is being ignored.*
- *[male voice] This is what we're talking about.*
[crowd shouting]
-This is the mayor. We got an hour and a half.
They're trying to buy it.
[crowd shouting]
- $$ *[female voice] It's not about how white you are
or how bright you are,$$*
$$*it's how right you are.$$*
-*[male voice] That's right.*
-*[female voice] The mayor Sharpe James.
Good day.*
[cars honking]
♪ [Cory Booker for mayor, yeah, yeah.] ♪
♪ [Cory Booker for mayor, yo,
Cory Booker for mayor.] ♪
♪ [Sharpe James, he's our mayor] ♪
[people shouting]
- *[narrator] At eight o'clock, the polls close
and the counting begins.*
- Sure. Sure. Sure.
- [female talking] Thirty and 40 and 45.
- *[narrator] One by one,*
*each polling sites reports its numbers.*
- I feel good. I really do feel very good.
It's been all positive.
- *[narrator] Cory surges ahead in the Latino*
*and Portuguese districts.*
*But from the predominantly black districts,*
*the results are very different.*
[crowd shouting]
[crowd cheering]
[crowd chanting]
Sharpe James is our mayor !
- [Sharpe] I'll be back! I'll be back!
Robert Treat Hotel! Robert Treat Hotel!
[crowd shouting]
[phone ringing]
- *[male voice] 110 of 161 districts
are reporting so far,*
*shows James up by 800 votes.*
*Eight votes. It's very, very close.*
[crowd chanting] Four more years!
[phone ringing]
- Hello!
Yeah!
Oh, my God.
Then it's over?
- *[narrator] Sharpe James got 28,300 votes.*
*Cory got 24,800.*
- *[Jimmy] He went upstairs to his apartment.*
- *[narrator] And how did he seem?*
- You know,
strong man,
he didn't wanna show it 'cause he had
a lot of troops behind him.
He didn’'t wanna show his weakness.
You know what I mean? He didn'’t show it.
But,
I knew.
It's gonna be better next time.
♪ [music] ♪
- We who fought so hard,
have now slipped a small end
of a larger wedge
into the door of this political machine.
Let us show our dignity
and our love for the city of Newark.
by not giving up our principle,
by not giving up our passion,
by staying persistent in this cause
and in this fight.
I want all of you to know,
who struggled so hard,
who put your faith in me and my leadership,
that I have not yet begun to fight.
Thank you all! God Bless you!
[crowd cheering]
- I've never had this kinda experience in my life,
where something bad happened
or against my expectations
that didn’'t turn out to be better.
For the better for some reason.
You know, in my mind
I keep of thinking of a victory speech
and not having to wing a concession speech.
But I wanted everybody to hold hands.
And I wanted to talk about the different people
that were holding hands that one moment,
and what those people are
able to accomplish and achieve.
And the power they were able to bring to bear
wasn'’t the power of an individual.
We're one race, one color, even the age groups,
I mean, there were teenagers,
kids that worked on the campaign to
And senior citizens.
[beep, beep beep]
[Cory laughing]
Feeling a bit, you know, embattled,
but also feeling incredibly really good.
We fought one hell of a fight
and I wish you could--
all the things that were going on.
It was just phenomenal.
- *[Cory] And I've learned something.
I learned something.*
Real courage is like the famous poem
by Maya Angelou, who says,
"You may be writing me down in history
with your bitter, twisted lies.
You may ground down in the very dirt
but like dust, still I rise."
[crowd cheering]
♪ [music] ♪